Today on The Rest Is History, the September massacres, the prisons and streets of revolutionary
Paris are washed with blood as we return to our incredible series on the French Revolution.
The homeland will be saved. Everything is in motion. Everyone burns to fight. While one part
of the people goes to the frontiers, a second digs our defences, and a third, armed with pikes,
will defend our cities and towns. We ask that whoever refuses to serve or to give up his weapons
shall be punished with death. The tocsin that will ring out will not be a signal of alarm,
but a call to charge against the enemies of the homeland. To vanquish them, gentlemen,
we need to dare, to dare, and to dare again. And then,
frontiers!
France will be saved.
So that Dominic was not Winston Churchill, although many people from the excellence of
the impression may think it was. It was actually a Frenchman, Georges Danton,
Minister of Justice in 1792, the Dominic Sandbrook to my Robespierre.
Oh, that's kind. Thanks, Tom.
And he's addressing the assembly on the 2nd of September 1792. And people will be able to realise
from this that we are back with the French Revolution.
We are indeed, Tom.
Our ongoing series, aren't we? And can I just say why I chose to do it in a Churchillian tone?
Do. Yeah, please.
Because I think there is a Churchillian quality to that, isn't it? That is a very,
very famous speech. It's all about defence of the fatherland, defence of the nation,
determination to fight on. And there is a Churchillian quality to it. And I thought
it subtly evoked a sense for British listeners of perhaps the resonance it has.
Yeah, it does have a huge resonance in France. So those words in French,
we need daring, more daring, always daring, to dare, to dare, to dare again, or however you
translate it. They're very famous. Lots of French school children will know those words.
And that, I think, gives you a sense of the position that we're in as we begin
season three of the French Revolution. This episode is very, very gory.
So,
listeners should be warned. It is absolutely revolting, particularly if you have children,
be warned. Because in today's episode, we will be turning to, I would say, perhaps the most
horrific episode of the whole revolution, the September massacres. So to give people a sense,
this is a moment when mobs are going to storm, basically burst into the prisons.
Or are they mobs? I mean, we'll be discussing, won't we?
Mobs or death squads. And they are going to club or hack a thousand,
people to death, some of them in very gruesome circumstances. And we'll be debating all that
later. But Tom, perhaps, first of all, we should remind people where we have got to. Now,
obviously, by reminding people, we don't need to do the whole previous two series again.
That would be too meta.
But yeah, it would. We'll never get out of it.
Okay, to give people a sense, we're in 1792. Tuileries has been stormed. France is at war,
and it's been at war since April. And it's gone incredibly badly so far. So France has
basically lost these little battles. So politics in Paris is defined by a feud between two rival
groups of Jacobins. So the first faction are called the Girondins, and they're under Brissot,
who you really liked, as I recall. I did like Brissot, yeah.
Yeah, a do-gooder. That's Brissot, isn't he? He's an abolitionist. He likes a literary salon.
He likes dinner with metropolitan people. He's a good man.
Yeah, that's Brissot. And then on the other end, another very Tom Holland figure, actually.
Yeah.
It's like the battle for your soul,
this Tom.
I know. This is why I find it so fascinating.
It's the Montagnard, the mountain, as they're called, under Maximilien Robespierre,
the kind of bony, Rousseau-loving. Another do-gooder.
Bewigged.
Yeah, a bewigged do-gooder.
Hates capital punishment.
Yeah, like you. The streets of Paris are full of armed young men. So these are the Fédérés
from Marseille and elsewhere. Tom, last time you talked about their importance in bringing
the Marseillais.
Yeah, that was the episode that we finished the last season on.
It was indeed.
And people will remember that the episode before that was the story of how these guys,
the Fédérés and the sans-culottes on the streets of Paris, the people who wear trousers,
the kind of artisans, the radicals, they stormed the Tuileries Palace. They launched a second
revolution. They slaughtered the Swiss guard. They effectively toppled the king and queen,
who'd been carted off to a prison called the Temple Fortress. But they also crucially arrested
about a thousand people who have since been crammed into the prisons of Paris.
This is a key point, isn't it? Because it's important to emphasise that although
it's the Swiss guards who end up being massacred, the opinion across Paris,
particularly among the sans-culottes, is that they were the victims.
Exactly right.
That it was the Swiss guard who had to blame for it. That the working people of Paris, who were
killed by the Swiss guards as they were defending themselves, are martyrs to liberty. And that this
is expressive of a kind of perniciousness. And that this is an expression of a kind of
pernicious royal attitude to the French masses. And therefore, there is a need for citizens to be
on guard against something like this happening again.
Exactly right. That's exactly right. So to give people a sense of the politics,
with the storming of the Tuileries, politics have been plunged into total chaos.
The king and his family are in the temple. In their place, the Legislative Assembly
has set up this executive, which is basically dominated by the Girondins and by Danton,
Minister of Justice. And they have said, listen, we are going to have to have
yet another constitutional kind of reboot. We're going to call for a national convention.
Now, this will be elected for the first time in near universal male suffrage. And everybody knows
this is basically going to call for a republic, that the monarchy is finished. But the Girondins,
who dominate this committee and who really dominate the assembly, it looks like they've
got everything their own way, but they don't. Because now they're having to kind of share power
in Paris with this new body that's been set up called the Insurrectionary Commune, which is the
local council. Which is a new body that's been set up called the Insurrectionary Commune, which is
dominated by much more radical people, and in particular by Robespierre. And if all this isn't
confusing enough, Robespierre says the Girondins, who are the people who got us into the war,
they're actually much too weak and too soft. They'll be much too soft on the royal family
and the enemies within. And they may actually be part of the foreign conspiracy, which sounds
bonkers, but that gives you a sense of the kind of the faction fighting, the paranoia that is around
in this point in 1792. I think there is actually
quite an easy way for people to get a handle on this, because this is the period where the
notion of right and left comes in, because it depends on where people congregate in the
National Assembly. And people on the right now, on the far right as we might anachronistically put it,
is the default position that had existed three or four years before. Royalists. Then you have
revolutionaries who have been trying to negotiate with the royalists and with the king and queen.
Then you have the Girondins. And then on the hard left, you have the Robespierres, the Montagnards.
Probably the easiest way to kind of get a sense of where all these various factions are. They are
now on a political spectrum that we in the 21st century can recognise.
Yeah. Although really, actually, you could argue that the fight is between two left-wing groups.
It is, yeah. Because the right is now, with the fall of the monarchy,
is finished. So it's now a fight between the left and the hard left. You might put it like that.
Yes, I guess you could make that point. And it's really important to say,
the atmosphere in Paris is haunted by fear and by a sense of coming catastrophe and a
apocalypse. Because all the time, the Prussians, they have crossed the border, they are coming
west. And the Duke of Brunswick, the Prussian commander, has issued a manifesto in which he says
explicitly, there will be an exemplary vengeance against the people of Paris. Paris is in the
firing line. I'm coming for you. And I'm basically going to wipe the floor with you.
So this is hence the Churchillian quality of Danton's defiance, defying the German invasion.
Yeah, exactly so. Exactly. And all through Paris, there are these mad rumours. People are saying,
there are loads of noblemen hiding in the sewers. They're poised to strike. They have hidden
weapons caches in churches, in the pantheon. And particularly, one of these rumours is that
there are criminals in the Paris prisons are going to break out. They're going to launch an
uprising. They are in league with these foreign villains. And the commune, the assembly, the
neighbourhood councils, which are called the sections, they are meeting almost permanently
around the clock. The city is lit up at night. There are several people who are going to be
killed. There are surveillance committees. There are troops in the streets. It is an
extraordinary atmosphere. You know, everybody is waiting for something to happen. And if we
pick up the story in the 26th of August. So on the 26th of August, 1792, terrible news reaches
Paris from the Eastern Front. The Prussians have been advancing for seven days and they have just
taken the fortress at Longueuil after barely a fight. Longueuil has surrendered and there's only
one fortress left, which is Verdun. So it looks like treason. It looks like treason, exactly.
And it looks like the Prussians can't be stopped. Some of the Girondins at this point say,
listen, you know, effectively it's 1940. We need to evacuate the government to Tours.
Which is a terrible, I mean, a fateful decision for them to push because Tours is a very royalist
and above all Catholic city, isn't it? So not a sensible place for them to choose
if they're in a life or death struggle with people on further to the left.
Yeah, it looks weak.
Well, it looks royalist.
It looks like they're not invested actually in the defence of Paris. Robespierre says,
no way, we should stand and fight in the defence of liberty. And of course,
Minister of Justice, this sort of big, fleshy, sort of corrupt, but very charismatic revolutionary
leader.
Another man with skin problems. And people who've listened to our first two seasons may remember
that skin problems feature throughout this.
I think it's fair to say, Danton, he's got terrible skin and he's got a taste for a brown
envelope. You know, he likes, he likes a backhander that he can spend.
And a lady.
Yeah. He likes a backhander that he can spend on a mistress and a massive selection of starters.
That's Danton's.
Modus operandi. Danton basically seizes the moment and he says, close the city gates of
Paris, put up barricades. I want, I want volunteers. I'm on recruiting stations everywhere.
And his charisma, his Churchillian charisma is really important. I think sort of steadying the
nerves. I mean, he really rises to meet the moment, but there is a dark side to all these
preparations because the provisional government with Danton as its kind of leading light issues
an official proclamation at this point. And it says, yeah, watch out for the Prussians,
but also watch out for the enemies within. Citizens, you have traitors in your bosom,
but for them the fight would already be over. Your active surveillance cannot fail to defeat them.
Now, what do they mean by the traitors within? They mean corrupt former advisors to the king,
ladies in waiting at the court who they say are all lesbians, speculators, hoarders, criminals,
the old Swiss guards, priests who have defied the civil constitution of the clergy, journalists who
have made up the name of the new king, in order to achieve a new government, but also to increase the
of the monarchy all these people they think are in the pay effectively of the sinister austrian
committee that is masterminded by marie antoinette and her friends in vienna i mean that's pretty
much the case isn't tom and on the issue of marie antoinette and her friends in vienna i mean they're
not wrong because marie antoinette has been conniving with the austrians so that's the thing
i mean it's important to say that so by the 28th of august two days later danton has now ordered
raids across the city raids on people's houses they're searching for guns they're searching for
enemy agents stolen documents letters so if you've ever seen documentaries or films about the french
revolution you've seen this sort of quite stereotypical image of a group of sans-culottes
with their kind of red hats and their pikes banging on people's doors thick stubble right
you've got an aristo hidden in the cellar or something that's where this is coming from lots
of historians at this point cite a diarist called rosalie julien she's a brilliant
diarist
actually on this period because she is married to a jacobin deputy now she is somebody who really
complicates your sense of the french revolution she's a very likable character she's very well
read she's very educated she's a big fan of russo a massive do-gooder and a reformer but she is
always writing in her diary the city is full of traitors and we have to root them out still more
traitors still more treason and i think those words are really important to understand what's
going to happen because she and so many other people are saying they're all in the prisons
all of these prisons are stuffed with traitors and as soon as our troops you know these volunteers
march out to face the prussians the traitors will seize their moment they will break out and massacre
the women and children of paris about half a year ago we did the battle of agincourt and henry v
is facing the french army but he's taken lots of prisoners and when he thinks that he's being
attacked from the rear he orders the prisoners killed because obviously the enemy within is
highly dangerous and there's a
slight i mean comparing the french revolution to the battle of agincourt not probably something
anyone's ever done before but there's a slight element of that to it i think i think it totally
is tom yeah i think there's there's a sense of the stab in the back is coming and there are all
these rumors about breakouts in the prisons so all through august actually there had been rumors
the paris police had been reporting rumors that people were about to break into the prisons
and i quote render prompt justice to the people inside them and in fact it's not surprising that
some newspapers and radical pamphlets and posters and things are very very explicit about what they
think we should do and i'll just give you two examples so one is a newspaper called the orator
of the people and it was edited by a guy called freron who's a friend of camille de moulin who
we've talked about before freron wrote this the first battle we shall fight will be inside the
walls of paris not outside all the royal brigands clustering inside this unhappy town will perish
in the same day the prisons are full of conspirators let the world know that we're
the world see how we judge them i mean that's ominous but not as ominous as this this is from
a guy called fabre deglantine who was a friend a great friend of danton and who was a poet he's not
a great ornament i think to the poetic profession when you read his words let us clear the ranks of
these vile slaves of tyranny let the blood of traitors be the first holocaust to liberty i mean
he literally used the phrase le premier holocaust so that in advancing to meet the common enemy
we leave nothing behind
to disquiet us and actually mara one of the most outspoken of all these journalists and has the
worst skin not coincidentally i think some mara says like basically citizens should go to the
abbey prison get the prisoners and i quote run them through with a sword and some of mara's kind
of defenders in the historical profession say oh that's just mara you know he talks he doesn't
really mean it but simon sharma says you know how do you know how are people supposed to tell
the difference so this is the climate on the 29th of august
the prussians reach verdun and verdun is the keystone of france's eastern defensive line if
you get past verdun you're into the valley of the marne and once you go through that you are heading
towards paris and verdun surrenders after three days to this impregnable fortress yeah the garrison
commander who'd said he'd never surrender either kills himself or is killed by the people of verdun
who basically don't fancy a siege at all we're like yeah we'll let the prussians in fine so
you've got a big long line of soldiers and the news arrives in paris on sunday the 2nd of september
the prussians are broken through and now you've got i mean it's an extraordinary scene you have
kind of church bells ringing there are cannons on the riversane sounding the alert and this is
when don tong gives his chilean address exactly don tong gives his address there are posters
going up across the city to arms to arms the enemy is at the gates now that afternoon we can be pretty
sure that something else happened but we can't see them so the union is looking for an aid or something
Can't be exactly certain what, because the documents were later destroyed.
They were destroyed in the events of 1870-71.
It's ironic, isn't it?
Another Prussian day trip to Paris.
So what seems to have happened is that some of the sections, these are the kind of neighborhood
councils in Paris, discussed how we eliminate these people in the prisons.
And there are a lot of people saying it's an unpleasant necessity, but basically somebody
has to do it.
Now, that's not to say the sections ordered it, but the tone has kind of been set.
At about this point, the chief prison inspector comes to Danton in the Hôtel de Ville in
City Hall, and he says, I'm genuinely worried about the safety of the people in the prisons.
And Danton says, je me fous bien des prisonniers.
I don't give a damn about the prisoners, like basically let them fend for themselves.
But to be fair to him, I mean, one of the reasons for that is that he can't spare people
from the barricades.
There's only a finite number of people.
And obviously the main threat from his perspective is...
The approach of the Prussians.
Tom, I'm so surprised at this.
I thought you were going to be on the other side of this equation, but it's very clear
to me now, from the way you've conducted yourself in this whole episode, that, you know, you're
going to take a very Dominic Sandbrook, princes in the tower line on this issue, are you?
Well, no, but I do think that there are reasons why someone like Danton, people in charge
of the revolution, might be unconcerned with prisoners and the security of the prisoners.
That relates to the overall situation in Paris.
Yeah, fair enough.
And also don't forget, everybody thinks the prisoners are total villains and traitors and
all of that stuff.
Of course.
But I think that saying, you know, we can't bother with them, it's justified by military
exigencies.
Fair enough.
Listeners can make up their own minds, can't they?
I have to say Theo agrees with you.
He's written in the chat.
Well said, Tom.
So that's nice.
So let's get into the story.
Sometime about 2.30 that afternoon, the 2nd of September, the news has come in from Verdun.
There was a group of prisoners being escorted through the city from the city of Verdun.
The Palais de Justice to the Abbey prison.
And they are royal officials, their courtiers, and their Catholic priests.
The streets are obviously packed with people because of the war panic.
And a lot of people shout abuse at them as they pass in these kind of carriages.
As they get towards the Abbey prison, which is in Saint-Germain-des-Prés, it's a former
abbey, hence the name, a group of people stop them.
These people are National Guardsmen, sans-culottes, a mixture of characters.
They stop the carriages, they drag the prisoners out, and they drag them into the nearby prison
section headquarters, which is a convent.
And there's a great crowd of people there, and the people are shouting, these are enemies
of the people.
You know, why take them to the prison?
Why not just get rid of them now?
Two or three of those prisoners try to break out, try to get away, or fight for their lives
or whatever.
There's a scuffle, they're beaten up, and they are hacked to death with knives, and
their bodies are left in the courtyard.
The rest of the prisoners are just, you know, 20 people or so, are just standing there absolutely
traumatized in shock, wondering what's going to happen.
An impromptu tribunal.
It's set up, and it declares them guilty.
Then one by one, in a very methodical way, they're led down the steps into the garden,
and there a group of men has assembled with knives, axes, hatchets.
There's a guy who's like clearly a carpenter because he's brought his saw.
And one by one, they are hacked to death.
It's important to say right from the beginning, this is the first incident.
It is not a mad frenzy.
It's not an orgy of violence.
It is quiet.
It's considered.
The guys take their time.
It takes about half an hour to kill all these men.
And then it is done.
And upstairs, the people who are still there, the room is absolutely full of people, and
they are debating, now that we've killed these people, why don't we just go into the Abbe
prison and do the same with everybody who is in there?
But again, not necessarily to kill them, to sit in judgment on them.
As we'll see, not everybody is killed.
You're absolutely right.
While that crowd is all debating and arguing about how they're going to do it.
A separate group breaks into another prison about a mile away called the Karm, it's a former
Karmalite convent.
So a lot of these prisons are convents and Abbes and religious houses that have been
converted.
In this prison, there are about 160 priests.
This crowd, again, organizes a kind of improvised tribunal.
They call out the prisoners' names one by one.
They take them out into the garden.
Some of them are shot.
Most of them, though, are hacked to death again.
Some of them try to climb over the walls or they even climb trees to get away.
But they are dragged back and finished off with knives.
Again, just to say, I mean, a quarter of them are spared.
Well, hold on.
115 people out of 160 are killed in this.
Absolutely.
Because I think it's easy to think that it is a total massacre.
Well, you wouldn't take your chances with that.
Of course not.
It's just really supporting what you were saying, that this isn't a kind of frothing
at the mouth, mad mob frenzy.
It's much more considered and therefore I think actually much more frightening than
that.
Agreed.
And by the way, we both gave different figures.
That's not because one of us is right and the other is wrong.
It's because every history book gives different figures on this.
So yeah, there is a lot of confusion about the figures.
Now meanwhile, the death squad has got started in the Abbe prison and also in some of the
other prisons.
And in all of them, it is the same kind of routine.
I think actually death squad is better than mob.
They're often described as mobs, but these are kind of organized teams of men.
They almost always hold this kind of tribunal.
They bring people out into the courtyard.
Once they've been found guilty and then they stab them or hack them to death.
And we only know one of the names of the people who organized this.
A guy called Stanislas Maia, who was a clerk.
He'd been at the Bastille.
He'd been a big figure in the women's March on Versailles.
And he seems to have been one of those people who's thrown up by these periods of revolution
and kind of chaos.
So a bit of a bully.
You could say he's the kind of person who would be a paramilitary leader and he loves
all this.
And he's obviously, this is his, his moment.
But it's interesting, isn't it?
That actually so few names are known and in large part, that is because in due course
to be a septembre as they come to be called is highly dangerous because it comes to be
seen as a terrible blot on the reputation of the revolution.
Not immediately though.
And I think that that reflects the fact that this is genuinely not being organized by the
big names, by Danton or Robespierre or whatever.
It's coming probably from the sections.
And the people who are organizing it are not people who will go on to great things to become
kind of famous names.
I think you're absolutely right, Tom.
I think the is being organized in, in so far as there is a sense of organization is at
a very, very sort of low level.
It's these kind of neighborhood councils, the commune.
We know that they talked about that's an instructionary council that's taking control of Paris.
We know they talked about it and they said your point, there weren't enough men to protect
the prisons.
We need them on the barricades.
Yeah.
And one of the communist committees issued a statement signed by Marat, the prisoners
are brigands who will slaughter our children and our women.
These acts of justice are indispensable to deter through the use of terror these legions
of traitors.
But it's not like Marat is being named as a guy who's leading it.
No, no, he's not going in.
He's inspired it.
But I think these are basically the people who had attacked the Tuileries, right?
Yeah, I think that's right.
It's people from the working class areas of Paris.
They are representative figures from the working population of Paris.
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, and we'll talk about in the second half about what the population of Paris think
of it, but I think you're absolutely right that basically they are pretty representative
of the city and of the streets, I guess.
It is the vengeance of the streets.
That's what historians who are more sympathetic to the September Massacre say.
On the bigwigs, the bigwigs know this is happening, but they don't do anything about it.
Danton says to Brissot, Durandat leader, the deaths are an indispensable sacrifice to appease
the people of Paris.
Yeah.
I mean, the husband of Madame Roulant, the great sort of linchpin of the Girondin sort
of social circle, he says the people terrible in its vengeance is exercising a kind of justice.
You know, they're making excuses for it and kind of, I mean, they do nothing about it.
That association of terror with a kind of justice, I think is exactly what's happening.
Yeah, I think that was very French Revolution, isn't it?
So that's the first day, but of course it's just the first several days.
The next day you get to Monday the 3rd.
The men at the Abbey prison.
The first prison to be targeted.
They're there for about 24 hours working away.
And meanwhile, other men have moved on to other prisons.
There's a seminary called Saint-Femin, which holds priests.
There's a convent called Saint-Bernard.
There's an asylum at Bicetre, which holds petty criminals.
Perhaps most shockingly, the Saupetrière women's hospice, which holds prostitutes.
And people have been joking, haven't they?
We should send Marie Antoinette to the Saupetrière.
So there, we're not talking about priests or courtiers or royalist journalists.
These people are actually poor, petty criminals, prostitutes and so on.
And this is, I think, where it gets particularly shocking.
So Bicetre, they killed probably 150, 160 people.
A lot of them are very young.
About 40 of them are probably under 18.
One of them is 12, two of them are 13, three of them are 14 and so on.
Saint-Bernard.
The people who were killed there, perhaps 70 of them, they're forgers.
And the Sainte-Colotte hate forgers because of the paper money.
They think the paper money is all a plot.
They think that the forgers have been working with counter-revolutionaries to undermine
it and to drive up grain prices.
So if you're a forger, you've got to go.
So David Andress, who's written a wonderful book on the terror, he comments
on this laconically.
September 1792 was not a good time to be a captured forger.
And that is put in the book.
I'm putting it mildly.
And not a good time to be a prostitute.
So Saul-Petriere, probably 40 prostitutes.
Or indeed a criminal generally, right?
Because you were talking about how throughout the revolutionary period, people have been
assuming that criminals are in association with counter-revolutionary forces.
And this basically seems to be why people are targeting people who are in for criminality
rather than for political crimes.
Yeah.
I think actually, Tom, since 1789, maybe I don't know enough about pre-revolutionary.
But I think certainly since 1789, you know, we talked about the grande peur, the great
fear in the countryside.
And that's a huge fear of brigands, isn't it, who are going to ride over the horizon
and trample your crops and burn because they're working with the local aristocrats.
Well, I think in Paris, there has been the same thing with criminals, you know, an anxiety
about street crime and a belief that crime in some obscure way is connected with the
court.
Well, again, David Andress, he makes the comment in his book on the terror that there were always
30,000 of them for some reason.
Yeah.
That again and again, this figure, there are 30,000 brigands, there are 30,000 criminals,
they're all plotting.
And clearly, it's just part of the temper of the time.
It's what people are obsessing about and terrified of.
Yeah, absolutely.
Now, actually, you made a really good point earlier on.
You were keen to emphasise that not everybody is killed.
The single most famous kind of insider account, the one that was best known in 1790s France,
came from somebody who did survive.
He was an army officer and a royalist journalist.
Yeah.
Called François-Journiac Saint-Méard.
And he was in the Abbey of Saint-Germain, a prisoner.
He wrote a book afterwards with a brilliant title, My Agony of 38 Hours.
I'd buy that.
And he says in that, basically, he was in the prison and he was in his cell and his
cell had a little window and he couldn't see into the courtyard, but he could hear.
And he said, basically, that was the execution ground.
And for hours, he was just sitting there in his cell, listening to people being murdered.
And he said the killers worked in silence and that made them even more terrifying.
He could hear people being led out and then the kind of grunting and the hacking of the
blows and all that kind of thing.
And he said all that he would hear, the only speech was that basically after everybody
was killed, the killers would shout, vive la nation, long live the nation.
And then they would move on to the next.
Now a guard, he'd made friends with a guard and the guard said to him, I'll let you watch
some of the interrogations before the tribunal so you can work out the right answers.
So eventually, 4th of September at one o'clock in the morning.
It's his day.
It's his turn.
Imagine that.
I mean, that's terrifying.
Somebody shouts out your name and you're led down the corridor and then you go into this
room which is packed with people, a lot of stubble, a lot of sweat and a group of men
at the end.
You have to answer these questions.
And he said the men who took him in had blood all over their shirts.
So he goes in and if his account is remotely true, and of course it may be exaggerated,
he did really well.
He was very calm.
He said, listen, I used to be a royalist, but I'm not anymore.
Circumstances have changed.
And of course I've changed my mind as we all have.
I've, I've never plotted and conspired with anybody.
I've never been interested in politics.
You know, I was just a journalist and you know, it's bad luck that I'm here.
And they acquitted him and they sent him home with an escort of son culotte.
And when he got back to his boarding house, his landlord who saw him coming with these
men covered in blood, got out his pocketbook to give these men money to basically pay them
off.
And the men said, oh, we don't do this for money.
Because they see themselves as agents of justice.
And I mean, just to emphasize this.
That actually of the prisons in which the killings are taking place, over half of those
who are detained in the prisons do survive this experience, which isn't in any way to
underplay, you know, I mean, almost half population of a prison being slaughtered is hideous,
but it's a glass half empty glass half full perspective, I suppose.
So it depends.
I mean, it's so interesting.
It depends which book you read.
I can tell you've been reading David Andrus' book because he's very much of the glass half
full, isn't he?
He's like, well, look at all the prisoners who survived.
Nobody talks about them.
Anyway.
This guy gave the right answers.
But of course, there are some people who cannot bring themselves to give the right answers.
And after the break, let's come to the most celebrated of all of those.
And that's somebody you've talked about before, Tom.
And I know you have a bit of a torn dress for this unfortunate lady.
It's Marie Antoinette's friend, the Princesse de Lamballe.
So we'll be coming to her story after the break and be warned, things are going to get
ugly.
And that is a very serious warning.
She received a saber blow behind her head, which took off her cap.
Her long hair fell onto her shoulders.
Another saber blow hit her eye.
Blood gushed out.
Her dress was stained with it.
She tried to fall down to let herself die.
But they forced her to get up again to walk over corpses.
And the crowd, silent, watched the slaughter.
So that is one of numerous accounts.
And we'll be looking at the range of what is reported about this death, describing probably
the best known of all the victims of the September massacres.
Who is?
The Princesse de Lamballe, who, as you mentioned just before the break, Dominic, we've talked
about before in our very first episode.
Episode one is season one in our episode on Marie Antoinette, that she was a very close
friend of Marie Antoinette.
She's of impeccable background, a princess of the House of Savoy.
She was notorious for being a bit dumb, was said to have a tendency to repeat clever things
that she'd heard people say and then pretend that she'd made it up herself.
But against that, there are other people who rated her intelligence quite highly.
She was a friend of Benjamin.
So again, a bit like Marie Antoinette, I mean, she's not entirely opposed to the kind of
traditions of sentiment and fondness for the poor that are feeding into the revolution.
But she becomes, like Marie Antoinette herself, a symbol of everything that is most rotten
and putrid of the Ancien Regime.
She is seen as kind of a vampire like Marie Antoinette.
She's assumed to be having a lesbian affair with her.
And this reflects the fact that the Princesse de Lamballe, unlike, say, Madame de Polignac,
another of Marie Antoinette's great friends who had fled, the Princesse de Lamballe had
stayed with Marie Antoinette and had served her as her mistress of ceremonies in the Tuileries.
And it is this loyalty to her which will doom her.
Yeah, that's right, Tom.
So just to give people a sense of what is coming, we had a big debate, didn't we, about
what reading we would come in with this half.
That is actually one of the less bloodthirsty, one of the least horrible of all the potential
readings that we could have.
Chosen, because nothing good is going to happen to her.
She's 42 years old at this point.
I'd always imagined her as being quite young, but of course, Marie Antoinette herself is
not terribly young at this point.
She's been with Marie Antoinette all this time.
She'd had a pretty terrible life, the Princesse de Lamballe.
Married at 16, widowed at 19, her husband probably gave her syphilis, so she couldn't
have children.
And her father-in-law had banned her from remarrying, so she's sort of stuck hanging
around Marie Antoinette.
And as you say, she is extremely loyal.
She's perceived as very haughty, isn't she?
I think that's because she's shy.
Yeah.
She's a nervous person.
Sickly.
Socially maladroit.
Yeah, absolutely.
But as you've said, and as you've brilliantly described in those episodes about Marie Antoinette
at the very beginning of the whole French Revolution cycle, she has always played a
very prominent part in the kind of pornographic demonology of the court.
Yeah, absolutely.
And I think this is so important for understanding the things that will come to be written about
her death.
Is that Paris has been saturated in appalling pornographic fantasies about Marie Antoinette
and about her female attendants and friends.
And this provides a kind of terrible context for what will happen to her and what will
be reported about her fate.
Yeah.
So on the 3rd of September, which is the second day of the massacres, the killers came to
a prison called La Force, where she has been taken with the other ladies-in-waiting and
with the royal children.
The royal children's former governess, Madame de Tourzel.
And there's a tribunal set up there of seven people.
The most famous of them is a radical journalist called Jacques Hébert.
He basically makes Marat look like a columnist for The Guardian.
He's kind of very extreme.
He's a bit Trump-esque, isn't he?
He has nicknames for his opponents.
Yes, incredibly aggressive.
So this tribunal has been working its way through the prisoners of the force.
They have a very strange sort of code.
If they say at the end of your hearing, vive la nation, then you are spared.
You're free to go.
If they say, you're free to go, you are killed.
So it's slightly confusing.
Anyway, the process to Lombelle is brought out and it's all actually very quick.
They say, did you know anything about the plot to kill the people by the Swiss guards
at the Tuileries?
So again, harking back to the sense that it's the guards who are at fault and it's a royal
conspiracy against the people.
And she says, no, I knew nothing about this.
Will you swear to liberty and equality and hatred of the king and queen?
She says, yes, I'll happily swear to liberty and equality.
But I cannot swear to liberty and equality.
I swear hatred of the king and queen is not in my heart.
Now at that point, by some accounts, there was a friend or an agent of her father-in-law
or something like this, who was in the room, who whispered to her, just said, say you'll
swear it and they'll let you go.
And she said, I have nothing more to say.
It's indifferent to me if I die earlier or later, I have made the sacrifice of my life.
And the tribunal says, very well, let Madame be set at liberty, which means you're for
the chop.
And then she is led outside into the courtyard.
And now what happens next is the subject of innumerable, undoubtedly sensationalized,
exaggerated, and probably entirely fictional accounts.
Many of them exaggerated, and many of them, frankly, probably fictional.
What do we actually know?
What we know is that the same day, the third, a group of sans-culottes delivered her body,
sans head.
To one of the sections.
Later the head was retrieved and these were buried privately by servants of her family.
That's what we actually know.
So we know that her head was cut off and was not there to be taken with the rest
of her body to the section notary.
Correct.
So there were a couple of issues and how she was killed, which is the subject of an enormous
sort of very prurient, frankly, pornographic speculation in the 1790s and afterwards.
And then there was.
We know that her head was cut off and she was released to her head afterwards, which
we know is a very, very famous part of the French revolutionary story.
So, the detail that you just mentioned about what happens to her head, which I think
does happen.
The story is that she gets put on a pike and it gets taken to the prison, the temple fortress
where the royal family are being kept.
And of course, Marie Antoinette, the friend and, in the opinion of the crowd, the lesbian
lover of the murdered princess.
And there were various accounts of what then happened.
Some say that the main Americans started the investigation, which was in 1556.
that marion tournette looked out of the window saw it screamed and fainted this seems an exaggeration
the likelihood is that she didn't see it she wasn't actually there at the time i think she
wasn't in the room right there's a story that the governor of the prison's wife sees it and
faints and people thought that was marion tournette i think it's possible they put the head on the
pipe by the way to the temple prison i think that sounds like something they might have done yeah i
agree and i think that as we'll probably explore later in the episode it's partly because parading
heads on pikes has become a part of revolutionary justice so the beheading of enemies of the
revolution the parading of their heads this is part of the language of justice on the streets
so you would almost expect that to happen there's also there's a terrible story about the duke of
orleans isn't there as was who's now become philip egalite one of the worst people who's ever lived
but again i don't believe this story there's a story that he's at the palais royal and he's
having dinner with some english friends english guests
and somebody brings in the head and he looks at him and he says oh that's lombard i know her by
her long hair anyway let's have uh let's have dinner again i don't think that happened i think
he's such a terrible man that i'd like to believe it did happen because it reflects very badly on
him i mean the question of whether the stories are true and won't go into all the details but
there is one particularly notorious account of what happened that i'm going to quote and anyone
listening who maybe has children or who doesn't want to hear it just block out the next couple
but this is a detail that was reported by a playwright and again it's intriguing how often
playwrights and fiction writers crop up in these stories he'd been sympathetic to the revolution
but seven years on when he wrote this he turned radically against it become a counter-revolutionary
he's a man called louis sebastien mercier and he wrote when the princess de lombard was mutilated
in a hundred different ways so already there we have you know the escalation of the kind of
torture porn if you like and the murderers had partaken of the bleeding morsels of the
of her corpse so he's saying they're eating her i mean the charge of cannibalism there is being
overt one of the monsters cut off her virginal part and made it into a mustache and the reason
for quoting this specifically partly it reflects the way in which counter-revolutionaries are
drawing on the kind of the libertine pornography of which the marquis de sade is the exemplar but
it also i think points to one of the ways in which the september massacres will be understood and
represented in the also the story of the september massacre of an efflorescence of literal demons
from hell monsters who have lost all trace of humanity and can perpetrate the most revolting
atrocities and this will be a way in which in the wake of the revolution throughout the 19th into
the 20th century counter-revolutionary traditions in france and beyond will interpret the september
massacres as being not a kind of clinical patient methodical elimination of people who they see as
criminals but a as parables of the civil war so the invasion of the revolution in france and the
but as an orgy of destruction and murder yeah like the stuff of a gilray cartoon yes exactly
so so my take on this is these stories are incredibly controversial among historians
and as we will see because we'll get into that in a little while my view is a lot of these stories
are clearly made up you know the stories of the most grotesque torture the stories of cannibalism
people drinking blood all of that kind of stuff it's part of a tradition of kind of political
invective to invent these stories but i think it's implausible to imagine that a thousand people
were killed without as it were people overstepping the mark you know without mutilation without rape
because there were suggestions that some of the prostitutes for example yeah in the sub-etch yeah
yeah were abused or raped is that inherently implausible no i think a lot of these these
are horrific killing they're not entirely surgical however i do agree with you that a mad frenzy is
the wrong way to think about it that it's a bad way to think about it and i think it's a bad way
it is pretty clear from a lot of these accounts like that account that we quoted before the
break of that guy who let go there is a kind of semblance of justice we know that the killers
took these tribunals that they're not all just sort of dancing around wearing people's body
parts as hats or whatever covered in blood that they are actually trying to take these tribunals
quite seriously we know that the crowds listen to the evidence and we do know that the killings
were carried out in silence because so many people talk about it and we know that the
massacres were carried out in silence because so many people talk about it and we know that the
crowds listen to the evidence and we know that the killings were carried out in silence because
so many people talk about it and we know that the murders were carried out in silence because
they were sounds like they were ritualistic killings that there was a kind of i dare i say
tom i don't want to give you you know a massive gift but it's kind of sacral dimension to it that
it was a purge it was a kind of purge of sin so it's often said i think correctly that there is
a presaging here of the notion of cleansing a state of disease that we see in the 20th century
today so i'm not going to get into that i'm just going to say that it's a purge of sin but it's a
totalitarian states, whether it's the fascists or the communists. But I genuinely think it is
also drawing on those Christian traditions because you talked about a holocaust. A holocaust is a
burnt offering to the gods. That's originally what it was transmuted into a Christian context
because these are all happening in abbeys, in convents. And the sense the inquisitors had
that they were doing God's work when they burn the diseased limb of the tree, this is very similar to
the language that you were having with the September massacres. I'm sure that there must
have been some kind of sexual sadism going on, maybe particularly at the Saint-Petrier. But just
to say on that issue, it's a Saint-Petrier where the fewest prisoners are killed. I think it's
something like 40, did we say? 35 to 40. But there are 280 or 90 there. So relatively speaking,
I mean, it's not like they're breaking into a prison full of prostitutes and
going,
going mad in the way that rakes in an Assad novel would. So I think that is, for me,
the most chilling thing about it. It is murder done in the cause of virtue.
Oh, I totally agree with that. I think that the people who do it think they're doing the right
thing. They think it's a necessary purge. But that is also why it's important for
counter-revolutionary propagandists to frame it as pornographic because that undermines the claim
of those who perpetrated these executions to be virtuous.
I think actually the pornographic kind of mode is the one that people
instinctively reach for because it is, Paris is awash with it. I think it's the natural genre
to pick. But I think it is natural for those who repudiate the notion that this has anything to
do with virtue. Okay. Let's just sum up the story. So it takes four days. The massacres in the
prisons last for four days. They die down on the morning of the 6th of September. To give you a
sense of what Paris looks like, the place is absolutely full of bodies. There are bodies in
the streets. There are bodies in the courtyards. There are bodies in the kind of corridors of the
prison. The rest of the prisoners, of course, have been
set free. So the prisons are empty and the commune eventually sends in people and says,
please scrub them down and wash them with vinegar. Get rid of the stench, get rid of the stains. But
in some of the prisons, La Force, for example, there's so much blood, they can't shift the blood
stains. Of course, a Tom Holland would say, some of the rooms are stained with blood, but some of
them are pristine and perfectly clean. Why not talk about those rooms? Anyway, we'll get into this in
a second, Tom, because we're going to talk about the historiography. There are copycat killings
elsewhere in France. So there are 44.
people, for example, that are killed in Versailles, a horrendous atrocity, actually. They are lynched,
they are beheaded in public, and their heads are stuck on the spikes of the palace gates.
So probably about 100 people are killed across France. But then in the next few weeks,
things die down. In the future episodes, we'll talk about why that happens,
the political transformation in Paris, and a very dramatic change on the battlefield.
Just to move towards a close on the September massacres. One question is, what did people in
Paris think of the war? What did they think of the war? What did they think of the war?
And we know people in Paris thought they were fine. They were completely fine. David Andrus,
who you've mentioned before, he makes a very good point that Parisians are used to public violence.
I mean, you talked about it, Tom, in that excellent episode you did on the guillotine,
the hideous rituals of the public executions, the idea of humiliating, degrading, and destroying
somebody in public. But Dominic, also what we talked about in that episode was how the revolution
equates itself with humanitarianism. And I think that's a very good point. And I think that's a very
good point. And I think that's a very good point. And I think that's a very good point. And I think
And it may seem mad to talk about humanitarian impulses in the context of the September
massacres. But I suspect that, I mean, maybe a majority of the people doing the executions
would say that actually they're not kind of publicly tearing people apart with horses or
anything like that. They're doing it expeditiously. And the whole tradition of hanging people from
lanterns and then parading their heads is seen as revolutionary justice, but is already starting to
be phased out. It's clearly a cause of embarrassment for the revolutionary authorities. And that is why
exactly as this is going on, we're going to have a revolution. And I think that's a very good point.
The guillotine is starting to be introduced and is becoming more and more the emblem of how
criminals should be dispatched. And the September massacres, I'm sure, must play a key role in that
process. That people in the revolutionary authorities think, okay, fine, I mean, it's
cruel necessity, but it would be better to do it with the guillotine.
Well, it's interesting that the papers at the time, they're not embarrassed about this at all.
This is a moderate paper, the Courrier Francais. The people made it their duty to purge the city
of all the criminals, to prevent a prison break.
The people took the extreme measure, but the only appropriate one, of forestalling the horrors that
were being prepared against them and of showing no mercy to those who would not have shown any to
them. But if you have a machine that can just slice a head off, you don't need courtyards full
of peoples with butcher's knives. Of course. I mean, we have diarists,
we have letter writers. There's a brilliant example of a guy, a merchant's son, an 18-year-old in
Peter McPhee's book on the French Revolution. And he wrote home and he said, there has been
a horrible massacre. He says, wherever you go, you see the bloody remains of mutilated bodies in
open graves. And then in the next line, he says, but it was the right thing to do. The prisoners
were plotting with the Prussians. We had to do it. And that diarist, Rosalie Julien, she said,
again, an atrocious necessity. The people terrible in their fury are avenging the crimes of three
years of vile treachery. And she talks in her diary. She says, people have had their heads cut
off. Priests have been eviscerated, but it's the right thing to do. And she says, people have had
their heads cut off. Priests have been eviscerated, but it's the right thing to do. Because we had to
save France. Now, the thing is, historians have grappled with this ever since. Because of course,
most historians, by and large, I would say, who write about the French Revolution, especially in
France, have been sympathetic to the revolution. And here you have an episode, which is, for me,
much more shocking than the terror. I mean, the victims and the terror, a lot of them are people
involved in politics, players in the games. They're players. These people are often young,
very poor, the criminals, the petty thieves.
The women, the prostitutes, the prince de Lamba. So, from the 21st century perspective,
I know Theo says, oh, you're always harder on French exponents of violence than you are when
the British do it. But I think even with that said, it's hard to contemplate this and to say,
oh yeah, they had to go, as Theo clearly thinks. I think you're being a bit harsh on Theo there.
You say that it's not comparable to the terror. I mean, lots of innocent people die in the terror.
And the difference is that death by the guillotine,
is more clinical than being hacked to death by people armed with knives and choppers. Don't you
think? I suppose so. I mean, I probably would choose the guillotine over being hacked to death
by a carpenter with a saw. At one o'clock in the morning? Yeah. So, the definitive French historian
of this was a guy called Pierre Caron. And he was writing in the 1930s. He was the head of the
National Archives in France. And he said, you have to understand it in the context of two things. One,
the fighting at the Tuileries and the thirst for vengeance. And the other is the mood of panic and
hysteria, as the Prussians.
And he said, you have to understand the war, the pressure, and all this kind of thing. And Caron,
for years, everybody said, he's the top man in the September massacres. He knows what's what.
And then 50 years later, our old friend, Simon Sharma, wrote his book, Citizens. Have you read
the passage where he talks about Caron? I have. He says his book is, and I quote,
a monument of intellectual cowardice and moral self-delusion. And he said, Caron is being far
too kind. This is basically the end of the world. And he said, Caron is being far too kind. This is
basically the end of the world. And he said, Caron is being far too kind. This is basically
anticipating the genocides of the 20th century. The same themes, we have to get them before they
get us. The same emphasis on a kind of what Sharma calls an armed sanitation, on purging France of
crime and sin. And you can see why Sharma, writing in the 1980s, very conscious of what had happened
in Europe 40 years earlier, why he looks at the September massacres and says, hey, don't make
excuses for this. This is unbelievable. And he says, hey, don't make excuses for this. This is
unbelievable, horrible and bestial. And he doesn't deny that there's a kind of efficiency
and a clinical nature to it. But he says that's what makes it all the more frightening.
But equally, he literally is repeating counter-revolutionary propaganda. So to quote him
from Citizens, when he's writing about Caron, some accounts, including that of Mercier,
so that's the playwright whose account of the fate of the Princess de Lombal we quoted,
insist on the obscene mutilation and the display of her genitals, a story which Caron dismisses
cloistered certainty of the archivist as intrinsically inconceivable. But we know
that didn't happen. And we know that because of research that has happened since he wrote
Citizens. So French historian Antoine de Bac, he's the guy who went through all the records
of the sections and found that the body of the Princess de Lombal was given to the notary of
the local section. And he recorded what had happened and none of these mutilations had
happened. So we know for a fact that that is counter-revolutionary propaganda. And that when
he dismisses it, it's not because he's some cloistered archivist, but because actually he's
right about that. That wasn't happening. So in this case, right, I agree with you,
it didn't happen. The thing is, do you take all the revolutionary sources on trust and say the
counter-revolutionary ones are propagandistic exaggerations? Or do you say that the truth
probably lies in between the two and that both of them are party pre? And actually the truth is
that we'll never really know. And this is the frustrating thing about this,
this is a classic example of historians projecting onto it their own political preconceptions. So you
give these, we talked about David Andrus. David Andrus is very much a man of the left. In his book
on the terror, you know, he says the September massacres are terrible, but then in the next
breath, he has a sentence like this. This is where he introduces the September massacres,
the people in arms exercised their right of self-defense against those they felt were
betraying them to the counter-revolution. You cannot imagine Simon Sharma writing that sentence,
can you?
No, you can't. But I think that's slightly to misrepresent what he's saying. I mean,
he is saying that that is precisely the horror. You know, they think that they're doing justice
and that is precisely why it is terrifying. You know, he's saying, I guess in the way that a
Christian would say about what the Inquisition did, and I think that there is an absolute
continuity there, as I've said, that it's the realization that you can launch a pogrom,
execute people in cold blood and feel that you are doing it in the cause of what is right.
That's what's frightening.
Yeah, but I don't think that excuses it. I think that makes it all the more terrifying.
No, but I don't think David Andrus thinks that either. I mean, I think that I'm no expert in
the historiography of the French Revolution, but the reading I've done of writers who are
on the left about this is that they do acknowledge that that is what is frightening.
Yeah.
You can commit atrocities and feel that you're doing it in the cause of right. And as I say,
it's like a Christian having to face up to, you know, the executions that have been done in the
name of Christ.
Well, are you not the person who did an episode about how the Nazis thought what they were doing
was right, and they were on the right side of history, and on the right side of kind of morality?
Yes. And that's where the analogy, I suppose Sharma's point about the sanitation kicks in.
It's absolutely the right one. So there's another brilliant book on the French Revolution,
the most recent English language survey. It's by a guy called Jeremy Popkin, an American historian,
professor at the University of Kentucky. And he is much more positive about the Revolution
than Sharma is. And he says in his section on this, he says, listen, if you think the
French Revolution is better than the experiments of the 20th century, for example, communism,
or indeed, Nazism, if you think the French Revolution is more progressive, as he clearly
does, he says, you should have a massive problem with the September massacres. Because he says,
the thing that is so frightening about them is that they are so cold-bloodedly political,
that they are people sitting down in committee rooms and saying, yeah, these people have got to
go. Go ahead and do it. Somebody organized the death squads. I mean, of course, they were
bottom-up to some degree. But there were people who led them. There were people who condoned it.
There were people who didn't intervene, all of that kind of thing. And in his version,
and indeed in Timothy Tackett and other historians, they say, this is a key step
towards what we call the reign of terror. The idea that maybe you'll make some mistakes and
some innocent people will be rounded up and killed accidentally, but it's actually better,
rather, to purge than to allow the evil, as they see it, to fester in your midst.
I agree. And that is, I think, what is frightening about it. But I think that
historians of all political persuasions would now see that as being what's frightening about it,
I think.
Well, because obviously we're going to be talking about this an awful lot when we get the terror
itself. But let's not get ahead of ourselves. The elections to the National Convention have
been happening all this time, and all the big names are standing. Brousseau, Robespierre,
Danton.
Marat. This new convention is going to meet on the 20th of September, and it is going to decide
the future of France, and in particular, something I know you'll be talking about in a couple of
episodes' time, the future of the royal family. But the question is, will this convention even
get the chance to do that? Because all this time, the Prussians have been coming closer and closer
and closer. So Verdun fell. The Duke of Brunswick is coming on. He's got 80,000 men. Every day,
he is coming closer to Paris.
He's now being pursued by a smaller French army under General Dumouriez, who is the foreign
minister who got France into the war in the first place. And by the third week in September,
the Prussians reach a place called Valmy, which is in the Argonne Forest. It's about 120 miles
from Paris. And rain is falling. The skies are overcast, and it's against this very kind of
turbulent backdrop that the Duke of Brunswick and the Prussians turn to finish off the French
and to come back to France. And so they're going to be coming closer and closer to Paris. And so
they're going to clear the battlefield for their final assault on the capital. And Tom, what happens
next will change the course of European history. Thank you, Dominic. Brilliant. What a cliffhanger.
So much more to come. Lots more drama. And of course, if you are a member of the Rest Is History
Club, you can listen to the next three episodes of this epic journey to the climax of the French
Revolution right now. We will be discussing in our next episode, Olympe de Gouges, the first,
feminist, the author of The Rights of Woman. We will be discussing the fall of the French monarchy,
and the climax will be the guillotining of Louis XVI. So it's one of the great stories,
not just of French history, but of history, full stop. And if you're not a member of the
Rest Is History Club, then you can listen to the next episode on Olympe de Gouges
this coming Thursday. Thank you so much for listening. Goodbye.
Bye-bye.